Matthew M. Lee

665 Huntington Avenue · Boston · MA mlee8@g.harvard.edu https://mmlee.me

Summary: I am a PhD student in Population Health Sciences at the Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health in the Department of Nutrition. My professional interests are focused on policies and interventions related to food systems and the environment that improve cardiometabolic outcomes, as well as the application of novel causal inference and simulation-based methods to advance population health and health equity research.

Education

Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health

2019-Present

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) in Population Health Science, Public Health Nutrition

University of California, Berkeley School of Public Health

2017-2019

Master of Science (MS) in Epidemiology

Thesis: Sugar-Sweetened Beverage Consumption 3 Years After the Berkeley, California, Sugar-Sweetened Beverage Tax

University of California, Berkeley

2012-2016

Bachelor of Arts (BA) in Public Health, Minors: Global Poverty, Music

Teaching

Teaching Fellow, Population Health Sciences 2000 A/B

2020-2021

Harvard Graduate School of Arts and Sciences

- Year-long core course for first-year PhD students in the Population Health Sciences doctoral program, covering
 concepts in sampling, estimation and statistical inference for regression models, model selection, survival and longitudinal analyses, measurement error, causal inference and mediation, and econometrics.
- Led lab sessions and weekly office hours with original lecture slides including applications using the R programming language, development and grading of homework and exam assessments, and primary role in course evaluation and refinement during transition to online/virtual learning.

Publications

- 1. Vercammen, K., Moran, A., Carnethon, M., McClain, A., Pool, L., Kiefe, C., Carson, A., Gordon-Larsen, P., Steffen, L., Lee, M. M., Young, J., Rimm, E., A Longitudinal Analysis of Food Insufficiency and Cardiovascular Disease Risk Factors in the Coronary Artery Risk Development in Young Adults Study. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. *In Press* (2021).
- 2. Lee, M. M., Altman, E., Madsen, K. A., Secular Trends in Sugar-Sweetened Beverage Consumption Among Adults, Teens, and Children: The California Health Interview Survey, 2011–2018. *Prev. Chronic Dis.* 18. doi:10.5888/pcd18.200399 (2021).
- 3. Falbe, J., Lee, M. M., Kaplan, S., Rojas, N. A., Ortega Hinojosa, A. M., Madsen, K. A., Higher Sugar-Sweetened Beverage Retail Prices After Excise Taxes in Oakland and San Francisco. *Am J Public Health.* doi:10.2105/AJPH.2020.305602. pmid: 32437271 (2020).
- 4. Ponce, J., Yuan, H., Schillinger, D., Mahmood, H., **Lee, M. M.,** Falbe, J., Daniels, R., Madsen, K. A., Retailer Perspectives on Sugar-Sweetened Beverage Taxes in the California Bay Area. *Preventive Medicine Reports*. doi:10.1016/j.pmedr.2020. 101129 (2020).
- 5. Mujahid, M. S., Sohn, E. K., Izenberg, J., Gao, X., Tulier, M. E., Lee, M. M., Yen, I. H., Gentrification and Displacement in the San Francisco Bay Area: A Comparison of Measurement Approaches. *Int J Environ Res Public Health* 16. doi:10.3390/ijerph16122246. pmid: 31242684 (2019).
- 6. **Lee, M. M.,** Falbe, J., Madsen, K. A., Secular Trends in Soda Consumption, California, 2011-2016. *Prev Chronic Dis* **16**. doi:10.5888/pcd16.180372. pmid: 31095919 (2019).
- 7. **Lee, M. M.,** Falbe, J., Schillinger, D., Basu, S., McCulloch, C. E., Madsen, K. A., Sugar-Sweetened Beverage Consumption 3 Years After the Berkeley, California, Sugar-Sweetened Beverage Tax. *Am J Public Health* **109.** doi:10.2105/AJPH.2019. 304971 (2019).

Works In-Progress/Under Review

- 1. **Lee, M. M.,** Kinsey, E., Kenney, E. L., Participation in US Federal Nutrition Assistance Programs and Childhood Obesity Risk: The Early Childhood Longitudinal Study 2011 (ECLS-K:2011). *Under Review* (2021).
- 2. †Clark, O., †Lee, M. M., Jingree, M., O'Dwyer, E., Yue, Y., Marrero, A., Tamez, M., Bhupathiraju, S., Mattei, J., Weight Stigma and Social Media: Evidence and Public Health Solutions. *Under Review* (2021).

Note: † denotes co-first authorship

Awards & Honors

Certificate of Distinction in Teaching, Derek Bok Center for Teaching and Learning	2021
Certificate of Distinction in Teaching, Derek Bok Center for Teaching and Learning	2020
Simon, Arpi, and Marie Simonian Research Excellence in Nutrition Prize	2020
Prajna Chair's Scholarship in Public Health Nutrition	2019
Reshetko Family Scholarship	2017

Work & Research Experience

Research Assistant 2020-Present

Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Department of Nutrition PI: Erica Kenney, ScD, MPH

• Led and supported data analysis, code review, and manuscript development and editing for projects related to nutrition policies aimed at addressing childhood obesity, improving food access, and reducing food insecurity – including evaluations of US nutrition assistance programs, of the Philadelphia, PA, sugary beverage excise tax, and of racial/ethnic disparities in food-related advertising to young children and their families.

Research Assistant 2020-Present

Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health, Department of Social and Behavioral Sciences The Childhood Obesity Intervention Cost-Effectiveness Study (CHOICES)

Supported microsimulation-based cost-effectiveness analyses related to US policy interventions and their potential
long-run impacts on child and adult outcomes, including health care spending, obesity, morbidity, and mortality.
Analyzed dietary and health data from representative samples including the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey, ran and synthesized output from simulation models, validated estimates against empirical data, and
developed methods to streamline post-processing of results.

Graduate Researcher 2017-2019

UC Berkeley School of Public Health Division of Community Health Sciences PI: Kristine Madsen, MD, MPH

- Managed evaluation of sugar-sweetened beverage (SSB) taxes in Oakland, Berkeley, and San Francisco to assess the relationship between implementation and beverage consumption, using a quasi-experimental difference-in-differences design. Supported analysis for *The Fit Study*, a three year cluster-randomized trial on the effects of BMI screening and reporting. Oversaw data collection, entry, analysis, and manuscript development and submission.
- Produced spatial data cross-linked with information from the California Department of Education, American Community Survey, and US Census for projects examining the role of targeted marketing of SSBs and the spillover effects of Physical Education related lawsuits on district PE policies in California.

Staff Research Associate 2016-2017

UC Berkeley School of Public Health Division of Epidemiology

PI: Mahasin Mujahid, PhD, MS; Patrick Bradshaw, PhD, MS

Managed research portfolio, including background literature reviews, Institutional Review Board (IRB) and ethics
approval and documentation, accounting and finance reporting, data management, manuscript preparation and
submission, and grant proposals. Provided teaching support for undergraduate-level Epidemiologic Methods course.

Research Assistant 2015-2016

UC Berkeley School of Public Health Division of Epidemiology PI: Mahasin Mujahid, PhD, MS

• Completed detailed literature review on the impact of community change initiatives on neighborhood collective efficacy. Coded, transcribed, and analyzed qualitative data using Atlas.ti.

Research Assistant 2014-2015

UC San Francisco Pediatric Hematology & Oncology

PI: Biljana Horn, MD; Robert Goldsby, MD

- Built comprehensive pediatric bone marrow transplant patient database in collaboration with Columbia University of risk factors associated with graft failure, including pre-transplant busulfan dose relation to chimerisms.
- Extracted patient medical records using EPIC EMR system and coordinated lab discussions and meetings.

Service

Union Steward 2020-Present

Harvard Graduate Student Union

• Supported department- and university-level organizing efforts to assess student needs, gauge contract priorities, and build social support amongst incoming and continuing doctoral students in the School of Public Health.

Executive Director / Housing and Employment Coordinator

2013-2015

The Suitcase Clinic

- Oversaw all volunteers, committees, and clinics aimed at providing health and social services to homeless and low-income populations in the Bay Area, including a course on issues on homelessness for UC Berkeley students.
- Built and maintained relationships with partners including The City of Berkeley and Berkeley Free Clinic, worked effectively to secure \$40,000 in funding, and initiated process for attaining 501(c)3 status. Initiated data collection and electronic services database to bolster institutional memory, and created stable budget and accounting process.

Global Poverty and Practice Fellow

2015

Makikita Quykuway

- Completed internship at Makikita Quykuway, a non-governmental organization dedicated to alleviating health and resource disparities in peri-urban informal settlements in Peru, as a recipient of the Global Poverty and Practice Fellowship from the Blum Center for Developing Economies at UC Berkeley.
- Conducted non-profit program evaluation and developed health education materials, worked in health clinics and supported child labor reduction interventions.

Skills

- · Programming languages:
 - Statistical analysis (R, Stata, SAS, Python, Stan)
 - Geographic Information Systems (R)
 - Typesetting (ET_FX, R Markdown, R Sweave, Markdown)
 - Presentations (react.js, R)
- · Software:
 - Qualitative analysis (Atlas.ti)
 - Reference Management (Endnote, Refworks, Zotero, Mendeley)
 - Microsoft Office/Google Suite (Microsoft Word, PowerPoint, Excel: Google Docs, Sheets, Slides)
 - Adobe Creative Suite (Photoshop, Illustrator, InDesign, Premiere, Lightroom, Bridge)
- Version control (Git/GitHub)
- Survey design (Qualtrics, Google Forms)